Guide to the Edward Thornton Hartman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward Thornton Hartman papers
1904-1943
1923-1943
MS 266
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(19 boxes)
Professional correspondence and subject files maintained by Hartman in connection with his career. The correspondence relates chiefly to Hartman's work as state consultant for the Massachusetts Department of Public Welfare (1923-1929). Important correspondents are T.N. Carver, W.A. Griffin, Joseph W. Kelly, Joseph Lee, Benjamin C. Marsh, A.D.K. Shurtleff, and Edwards Albert Park. The major portion of the papers consists of topical files, principally on planning and on zoning, which was of particular interest to Hartman, who was active in the writing of zoning laws in twenty-eight states. The files, which contain printed matter, notes on legal decisions and practical problems, offer thorough documentation of all aspects of zoning in the urban environment. Twenty-five cities in Massachusetts are included in the planning section as part of a series of Master Community Surveys, 1912-1940.
Hartman, Edward Thornton, 1869-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Mr. and Mrs. E.T. Hartman, 1942.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, 1904-1940s, undated. II Subject Files, [circa 1863-1940s].
Scope and Contents
The Edward Thornton Hartman Papers document the professional career of Edward Thornton Hartman (1869- ), a housing, planning, and zoning expert in Massachusetts. The collection is arranged in nineteen (19) boxes and totals six and one-half (6.5) feet. Span dates for the collection are 1904-1940s, with bulk dates of 1923-1943.
Hartman's professional employment included service as: secretary of the Massachusetts Civic League (1904-1920); managing director and secretary of the Child Federation, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (1921-1923); and state consultant on Housing and Planning, Department of Public Welfare, Boston, Massachusetts (1923-1929). Hartman also served as president of the Massachusetts State Conference on Social Work, vice president of the American Civic Association, director of the American Federation of Arts, and director of the National Housing Association.
The Hartman Papers are organized in two series, maintaining the organization of files constructed by the donor: I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1904-1940s, n.d., II. SUBJECT FILES, [ca. 1863-1940s].
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, contains the professional correspondence of Edward Hartman. Little or no insight into the private man and his personal life is available in this material. These letters, arranged chronologically, consist of one folder of items relating to the Massachusetts Civic League (folder 1), and one folder of items relating to the Child Federation of Philadelphia (folder 2). All remaining correspondence relates to Hartman's work as state consultant for Massachusetts' Department of Public Welfare (folders 3-22).
Hartman's correspondence as a state consultant sheds light upon the thoughts and actions of municipal, town, and state officials and planners from 1923-1940s. Specifically, there is much correspondence with Massachusetts town and city officials, containing factual and theoretical discussions of the necessary components for zoning and planning programs in the 1920s and 1930s. Hartman corresponded with individuals from cities and towns such as: Greenfield, Leominster, Lexington, Medford, Nantucket, Saugus, Swampscott, and Taunton. To a lesser degree, Hartman corresponded with municipal representatives from across the nation. These correspondents included: architects, attorneys, boards of selectmen, chambers of commerce, city clubs, city hall representatives, city solicitors, highway commissions, journals, planning committees, and zoning boards. Among the common topics of interest in these letters are: education, housing, legislation, real estate, recreation, and traffic.
Much of Hartman's professional work focused on the analysis and application of the principles of zoning into the municipal environment, and his expertise and committment to the concept of zoning is amply reflected in his correspondence. Hartman undertook a comprehensive study of zoning decisions in Massachusetts courts and the Supreme Court. In 1928 he concluded that the many traumas facing American communities demanded zoning action, "by which lot sizes may be established, that is minimum sizes, front, side and rear yards may be provided, and residential districts may be protected from encroachment by any kind of commercial or industrial activity. These are all essential." By 1939 Hartman could claim a direct role in writing some twenty-eight state laws.
Correspondence relating to the Massachusetts Civic League (folder 1) consists of letters from the South Park Commissioners (Chicago), Commission on Immigration and Housing of California, State Charities Association, and various state civic leagues. These letters relate to proposed social programs, the legality of city and state zoning laws, and the role of state civic leagues. Individual correspondents, whose letters deal with these same subjects, include: T.N. Carver, W.A. Griffin, Joseph W. Kelly, Joseph Lee, Benjamin C. Marsh, and A.D.K. Shurtleff.
Letters pertaining to Hartman's work at the Child Federation of Philadephia are arranged in folder two. These nine letters include correspondence with Edwards Albert Park of Yale University's Department of Pediatrics, the American Red Cross, and the Child Health Organization of America. These letters focus on the topics of health and housing concerns (see also: Series II, folder 28).
Series II, SUBJECT FILES, contains an alphabetical arrangement of research and reference files compiled by Hartman. Examples of Hartman's addresses and writings, both published and unpublished, are arranged in this series (folders 38-44). The topics of these works include: housing reform, state and local legislation, town and village improvement, recreation, health, regionalism, traffic control, real estate, zoning, architecture, neighborhood centers, the Massachusetts Civic League, and improvement societies.
Three major subject headings in this series are: "Planning," "Planning and Zoning," and "Zoning." Planning files (folders 64-101) contain information on: city planning, 1907-1939, n.d.; on a Master Community Survey, 1912-1940, n.d.; and on subdivision controls, [ca. 1912-1939, n.d.]. Master Community Surveys were coordinated, extensive surveys designed to elicit and involve the entire population of an area. Planning files contain printed material and writings organized under headings for individual states. Files for Massachusetts are subdivided alphabetically by city and town. Among the locales represented in these files are: Amherst, Andover, Belmont, Billerica, Boston, Cambridge, Concord, Charlestown, Foxboro, Great Barrington, Greenfield, Leominster, Lexington, Marion, Marblehead, Medford, Needham, Peabody, Plymouth, Quincy, Reading, Saugus, Watertown, Wayland, and Worcester (folders 91-97).
Planning and zoning files (folders 102-115) consist of printed material and notes on various state and federal court decisions from 1899-1939, n.d. (folders 102-113). Additional files in this section contain writings and notes on practical problems (folder 115) in planning and zoning.
Zoning files (folders 135-149) consist of files of general information and administration, lot sizes, maps, Massachusetts, and problems. These files contribute substantially to Hartman's thorough documentation of all aspects of zoning in the urban environment.
Additional material relating to zoning is arranged in an index card file (boxes 15-19). Headings for planning, zoning - miscellaneous, and court decisions all contain further data on zoning-oriented topics.
Other files of interest in this series include those for the subjects of: charity (folder 27), neighborhood units (folder 55), traffic and traffic control (folder 128), traffic problems (folders 129-131), and villages (folder 134). These files contain a variety of printed material and writings which focus on the professional response to such developments in the 1920s and 1930s.
Biographical / Historical
Housing, planning, and zoning expert; secretary of the Massachusetts Civic League, 1904-1920; managing director and secretary of the Child Federation, Philadelphia, 1921-1923; state consultant on Housing and Planning, Department of Public Welfare, Boston, 1923-1929; president of the American Civic Association, director of American Federation of Arts, director of National Housing Association.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
City planning -- Massachusetts; Land use -- Massachusetts; Regional planning -- United States; Zoning -- United States; Massachusetts -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Massachusetts -- Surveys; New England; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1918-1945; City planners; Carver, Thomas Nixon, 1865-1961; Griffin, W. A.; Hartman, Edward Thornton, 1869-; Kelly, Joseph W., 1926-; Lee, Joseph, 1862-1937; Marsh, Benjamin Clarke, 1877-1952; Park, Edwards A. (Edwards Albert), 1877-1969; Shurtleff, A. D. K.; Massachusetts. Department of Public Welfare
- Correspondence, 1904-1940, undated; Series I; 1 linear foot (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged chronologically, with undated material filed at the end of the series.
  - 1904-1931 January 1904-1931 January (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
  - 1931 February - 1940, undated 1931 February - 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 13-22)
- Subject Files, [ca. 1863-1940s]; Series II; 6 linear feet (17 boxes)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  A card index file, also arranged alphabetically by subject, is organized in boxes 15-19.
  - Billboards, [ca. 1920-1935, undated] (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Boston University and Dartmouth College--public welfare, 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Bridges, 1900-1920 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Catholic attitudes in education, 1863, [ca. 1919-1920] (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Charity, [ca. 1915-1921] (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Child Federation, 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Cities, 1913-1931 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Citizenship and government, [ca. 1913-1935] (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Clubs, [ca. 1928] (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Cooperatives, [ca. 1926-1937] (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Culture, [ca. 1927-1936] (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Depression of 1929, [ca. 1931-1937] (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Eton, Walter Prichard--Address to the young people, Unitarian Laymen's League, Philadephia, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Federal home loan bank board, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Grade crossings, [ca. 1920-1930] (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Hartman, Edward Thornton
    - Addresses and articles
      - 1906-1936, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 38-42)
      - Newspaper articles, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Notes and drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - American Architect —articles and correspondence, [ca. 1924-1925] (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Autobiographical data and estimates of him by others, [ca. 1909-1914] (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Catalogue of zoning and planning material in his library, [ca. 1923-1935] (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Letters to editors, [ca. 1912-1937] (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Health, [ca. 1915-1924] (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Highways, [ca. 1920-1929] (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Housing, 1912-1939 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Manufactures—census in Massachusetts, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Muscle Shoals, Alabama, [ca. 1926-1927] (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Neighborhood units, [ca. 1925-1934] (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Pan American conference, Havana, 1940 July (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Real estate, [ca. 1930s] (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - "The Social Settler," The Boston Transcript, 1908-1909 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - War profits, 1940s (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Miscellaneous, 1940s (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Northwest Regional Council, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Parks, 1905-1934 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Photographs and illustrations, undated (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Planning
    - Adoption and enforcement, 1932, undated (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Building heights, [ca. 1922-1930] (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Charts (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - City
      - 1907-1915 (Box 6, Folder 67)
      - 1916-1939, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 68-72)
    - Economic phases, [ca. 1902-1939, undated] (Box 7, Folder 73-74)
    - Foreign cities, [ca. 1926-1932] (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - General, 1925-1937 (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - Master Community Survey, [ca. 1912-1940, undated] (Box 8, Folder 77-78)
    - Problem of sunlight, [ca. 1917-1930] (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Regional approaches, [ca. 1924-1931] (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Regional New England, [ca. 1927-1937] (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Regional papers, 1927-1934, undated (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Schools, [ca. 1922-1939] (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - Subdivision controls, [ca. 1912-1939, undated] (Box 8, Folder 84-86)
    - Taxation, [ca. 1930's] (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - U.S.
    - California, [ca. 1913-1934] (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Connecticut, [ca. 1933, undated] (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Maryland, [ca. 1918-1924] (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - Massachusetts by towns
      - A - B, [ca. 1930s] (Box 9, Folder 91)
      - C - K, [ca. 1925-1937, undated] (Box 9, Folder 92)
      - L, [ca. 1925-1937] (Box 9, Folder 93)
      - M, [ca. 1924-1938] (Box 9, Folder 94)
      - N - P, [ca. 1926-1931, undated] (Box 9, Folder 95)
      - Q - R, 1926-1937 (Box 10, Folder 96)
      - S - Y, 1913-1936 (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - Michigan, New Hampshire, New Jersey, [ca. 1919-1931] (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - New York, [ca. 1917-1938] (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, [ca. 1920-1938] (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Rhode Island, Tennessee, Texas, Vermont, Virginia, Washington, Wisconsin, [ca. 1925-1930, undated] (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - Planning and Zoning
    - Court decisions and laws
      - 1899, 1912-1929 (Box 10, Folder 102-105)
      - 1930-1939, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 106-113)
    - New frontiers, [ca. 1928, undated] (Box 11, Folder 114)
    - Practical problems, [ca. 1927-1936] (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Planning boards—procedures, [ca. 1936] (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Press—responsible journalism
    - General, 1908-1931 (Box 11, Folder 117)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Public Utilities
    - General, 1923-1930 (Box 12, Folder 119)
    - General and newspaper clippings, 1932-1939, undated (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Single Tax, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Social programs, 1911-1939, undated (Box 12, Folder 122-123)
  - Soil-stripping in New England, 1935-1940 (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Statistics, 1908-1924, undated (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Technocracy, [ca. 1932-1933] (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - Tennessee Valley Authority, 1933-1938 (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - Traffic and traffic control, 1923-1939 (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - Traffic problem
    - General, 1924-1938, undated (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 12, Folder 130)
    - Pamphlets, 1928-1937, undated (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Trusts and the public
    - General, 1926-1934 (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated material (Box 13, Folder 133)
  - Villages, 1904-1937 (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - Zoning
    - Administration, 1925-1935, undated (Box 13, Folder 135-136)
    - General, 1916-1938, undated (Box 13, Folder 137-142)
    - Lot sizes, 1934-1939, undated (Box 13, Folder 143)
    - Maps, 1926-1937 (Box 13, Folder 144)
    - Massachusetts, undated (Box 14, Folder 145-146)
    - Problems, 1920-1938, undated (Box 14, Folder 148-149)
  - Index card file, [ca. 1920-1940]
    - Advertising (Box 15)
    - Airports (Box 15)
    - Amenities (Box 15)
    - Architectural control (Box 15)
    - Automobiles (Box 15)
    - Ballyhoo (Box 15)
    - Betterments (Box 15)
    - Blighted areas (Box 15)
    - Citizen action (Box 15)
    - Conservation (Box 15)
    - Cooperation (Box 15)
    - Democracy (Box 15)
    - Dinosaur cities (Box 15)
    - Economic planning (Box 15)
    - Education (Box 15)
    - Excess condemnation (Box 15)
    - Fire (Box 15)
    - Forest trees (Box 15)
    - Government forms (Box 15)
    - Health (Box 15)
    - Housing (Box 15)
    - Industrialism (Box 15)
    - Land (Box 15)
      General
      See: "Railroads," box 17
    - Lecture notes (Box 15)
    - Life (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Planning
      - Planning, regional (Box 16)
      - School plants (Box 16)
      - Sidewalks (Box 16)
      - Streets—roads design (Box 16)
      - Subdivisions (Box 16)
      - Traffic (Box 16)
      - Traffic accidents (Box 16)
    - Politics (Box 16)
      See also: "Privilege," box 17
    - Population trends (Box 16)
    - Press—radio (Box 16)
    - Privilege (Box 17)
      See also: "Politics," box 16
    - Public services (Box 17)
    - Radio (Box 17)
    - Railroads (Box 17)
    - Recreation (Box 17)
    - References—index (Box 17)
    - Securities (Box 17)
    - Stories (Box 17)
    - Taxation—tariff (Box 17)
    - Unemployment (Box 17)
    - Utilities
      - Planning by-passes (Box 17)
      - P. Corner Radii (Box 17)
      - Freeways (Box 17)
      - Grade crossings (Box 17)
      - Master plan (Box 17)
      - P. neighborhood units (Box 17)
      - Promotional (Box 17)
    - Zoning—miscellaneous
      - Accessory uses (Box 17)
      - Administration (Box 17)
      - Appeals (Box 17)
      - Balanced zoning (Box 17)
      - Building lines (Box 17)
      - Bulk zoning (Box 17)
      - Decisions (Box 17)
      - Earth products (Box 18)
      - Filling stations (Box 18)
      - Highway zoning (Box 18)
      - Lot sizes (Box 18)
      - Neophobia (Box 18)
      - Non-conforming (Box 18)
      - One-family districts (Box 18)
      - Promotional (Box 18)
      - Spot zoning (Box 18)
      - Techniques (Box 18)
      - Trailers (Box 18)
    - Court Decisions
      - General (Box 19)
      - City and town planners (Box 19)
      - Decisions (Box 19)
      - Housing—data (Box 19)
      - Health (Box 19)
      - References (Box 19)